A Guide to the University of Virginia School of Medicine Student Notebook Collection, 1836-1943
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
- Student notebook: Pediatrics 2 and Preventive Mediciine and Epidemiology 1942 February 26-September 3, ADS notebook (Box-folder 013-008)
  Professors: Pediatrics: William Wirt Waddell, Jr. (Associate Professor of Pediatrics) and William Herndon Pearson (Instructor of Orthodontia); Preventive Medicine and Epidemiology: George McLean Lawson (Professor of Preventive Medicine and Bacteriology) and Thomas Shepherd Englar (Professor of Public Health and Hygiene). The lecturers include Drs. [William Wirt] Waddell, [McLemore] Birdsong and [George McLean] Lawson.
- Student notebook: Medicine 5 1942 February 27-August 11, ADS notebook (Box-folder 013-009)
  Professors: Eugene Markley Landis (Professor of Internal Medicine), Henry Bearden Mulholland (Professor of Practice of Medicine), James Edwin Wood (Professor of Practice of Medicine), Staige Davis Blackford (Assistant Professor of Medicine), Oscar Swineford, Jr. (Assistant Professor of Medicine), Andrew DeJarnette Hart (Professor of Clinical Medicine and Director of Student Health), John Randolph Tucker Carmichael (Instructor of Medicine), and John Lippincott Guerrant (DuPont Service Fellow in Internal Medicine). The lecturers include Drs. [Byrd Stuart] Leavell, [Eugene Markley] Landis, [Oscar] Swineford, [William Gayle] Crutchfield. Drs. [Henry Bearden] Mulholland, [Staige Davis] Blackford, [Everett Cato] Drash, [John Osborne] McNeel, and Wood held clinic.
- Student notebook: E.N.T., Syphilology, and Medical Jurisprudence 1942 March 29-November 24, ADS notebook with drawings (Box-folder 014-001)
  Professors: Diseases of Ear, Nose and Throat: Fletcher Drummond Woodward (Professor of Diseases of Ear, Nose and Throat), Edwin Weisman Burton (Professor of Diseases of the Eye), Cuthbert Tunstall (Assistant Professor of Diseases of Ear, Nose, and Throat), Glassell Slaughter Fitz-Hugh (Instructor of Otolaryngology), and Fielding Jason Crigler (Instructor of Ophthalmology); Syphilology: Dudley Crofford Smith (Professor of Dermatology and Syphilology), Walter Croft Herold (Instructor of Dermatology and Syphilology), and Joseph Leigh Hundley (DuPont Service Fellow in Physiology); Medical Jurisprudence: James Alexander Waddell (Professor of Pharmacology, Materia Medica, and Toxicology) and Herbert Silvette (Assistant Professor of Pharmacology, Materia Medica and Toxicology). The lecturers include Drs. [James Alexander] Waddell, [Dudley Crofford] Smith, and [Fletcher Drummond] Woodward.
- Student notebook: Roentgenology and N & P 2 1942 July 7-December 1, ADS notebook with drawings (Box-folder 014-002)
  Professors: Roentgenology: Vincent William Archer (Professor of Roentgenology), George Cooper (Assistant Professor of Roentgenology), Ivor David Harris (Instructor of Roentgenology), Dr. Adams, and Dr. Pearce; Neurology and Psychiatry: David Cole Wilson (Professor of Neurology and Psychiatry). The lecturers include Drs. [Vincent William] Archer, [David Cole] Wilson, and [George] Cooper.
- Student notebook: Medicine 6 1942 August 6 - 1943 February 25, ADS notebook with drawings (Box-folder 014-003)
  Professors: Eugene Markley Landis (Professor of Internal Medicine), Henry Bearden Mulholland (Professor of Practice of Medicine), James Edwin Wood (Professor of Practice of Medicine), Staige Davis Blackford (Assistant Professor of Medicine), Oscar Swineford, Jr. (Assistant Professor of Medicine), Andrew DeJarnette Hart (Professor of Clinical Medicine and Director of Student Health), John Randolph Tucker Carmichael (Instructor of Medicine), and John Lippincott Guerrant (DuPont Service Fellow in Internal Medicine). The lecturers include Drs. [Eugene Markley] Landis, [Henry Bearden] Mulholland, and Drs. Mulholland, Wood, and [Oscar] Swineford held clinics.
- Student notebook: Preventive Medicine and Epidemiology 2 1942 September 28-December 5, ADS notebook (Box-folder 014-004)
  Professors: George McLean Lawson (Professor of Preventive Medicine and Bacteriology), and Thomas Shepherd Englar (Professor of Public Health and Hygiene). The lecturers include Dr. [George McLean] Lawson.
- Student notebook: "Legal Medicine or Medical Jurisprudence, Outline of Course supplemented with Related Questions and Topics," Medical Department, University of Virginia, J. A. Waddell, University Press, 1942. 1942 October 27, TDS booklet with A marks (Box-folder 014-005)
  The booklet belonged to Armistead P. Booker. For more information on Booker see Box-folder 011-001.
  Professors: Medical Jurisprudence: James Alexander Waddell (Professor of Pharmacology, Materia Medica, and Toxicology) and Herbert Silvette (Assistant Professor of Pharmacology, Materia Medica and Toxicology)
- Student notebook: Laboratory Notebook in Physiology 1935 November 6, TDS notebook with A notes, 1 TLS copy (Box-folder 014-006)
  The notebook was done by Malcolm Foote Sher and Charlotte Swaney. Sher donated it in 1992. According to the "University of Virginia Record," Malcolm Foote Sher and Charlotte Ellen Swaney both received their MD degrees on June 13, 1938.
- Student notebook: Surgery 1936 January - 1937 June, ADS notebook, 1 TLS copy (Box-folder 014-007)
  The notes were taken by Malcolm Foote Sher. According to the "University of Virginia Record," Malcolm Foote Sher received his MD degrees on June 13, 1938. The notebook is divided into sections: General Principles by Dr. [Edwin Partridge] Lehman, Abdominal Surgery by Dr. [Edwin Partridge] Lehman, General Surgery by Dr. [Charles Bruce] Morton, Thoracic Surgery by Dr. [Everett Cato] Drash, Sympath. Surgery by Dr. [Edwin Partridge] Lehman, Neuro Surgery by Dr. [Claude C.] Coleman, Urology by Dr. [John Henry] Neff and Gynecology by Dr. [Charles Bruce] Morton.
- Student notebook: Medicine, Materia Medica and Chemistry [1836], ADS notebook, 1 TL (Box-folder 014-008)
  The notes were taken William H. Harding. According to the "Catalogue of the Officers and Students of the University of Virginia," Harding attended sessions in 1835-36 and 1836-37. According to the accompanying letter from Palinurus Antiquarian Books, the lectures were given by John Patten Emmet. The letter also indicates that Harding was from a Virginia family in Northumberland County whose estate and plantation still stand, that he practiced medicine and served in the Virginia General Assembly before an untimely death. In the back of the notebook are fragments of letters to people including Ann H. George and his uncle.
- Student notebook: Physiology and Pharmacology 1922 September 20 - 1923 May 25, ADS notebook, 1 TL (Box-folder 015-001)
  The notes were taken by Porter B. Echols. According to the "Catalogue of the Officers and Students of the University of Virginia," Porter Burks Echols graduated June 1925.
  The lecturers include Drs. [Theodore] Hough and [James Alexander] Waddell. The notebook was donated by Dr. Porter B. Echols, Jr. in May 2008.
- Student notebook: Physical Diagnosis 1923 Jan 16 - 1925 February 25, ADS notebook (Box-folder 015-002)
  The lecturers include Drs. [Allen F.] Voshell, [John Staige] Davis, [William Hall] Goodwin, [William Douglas] Macon, [William Edward] Brown, and [James Alexander] Waddell. The notebook was donated by Dr. Porter B. Echols, Jr. in May 2008.
- Student notebook: Practice of Medicine, Diseases of Nervous System, Case teaching, Insanity 1924 April 28 - 1925 April 25, ADS notebook (Box-folder 015-003)
  The lecturers included Drs. [Lawrence T.] Royster, [Leroy Adelbert] Calkins, and [John Staige] Davis. The notebook was donated by Dr. Porter B. Echols, Jr. in May 2008.
- Student notebook: Anatomy 1873 October 4 - 1874 June 22, ADS notebook (Box-folder 015-004)
  The notes were taken by Charles Shepherd Webb. According to his brief autobiography, when he attended the University of Virginia, he took a "thorough course in the theoretical branches and then went to the University of New York to get the benefit of the hospitals." He graduated with the degree of M.D. from the University of New York.
  The UVa lecturer was John Staige Davis in anatomy. The notebook also contains notes that were given by Professor Darling at the University of New York and another section on materia medica.
  The notebook was donated by Ann W. McDowell, Webb's granddaughter, in March 2010.
- Student notebook: Notes on Chemistry and Medicine, 1839 September 16 - 1840 March 30, ADS with drawings notebook (Box-folder 016-001)
  The notes were taken by Jethro Meriwether Hurt. Hurt attended the University of Virginia for the 1839-40 session and studied Chemistry, Medicine, and Anatomy and Surgery. He graduated from the University of Pennsylvania Medical School in 1841.
  (September 1839-1840 at the University of Virginia): Notes on chemistry (Dr. [John P.] Emmet) -- Chlorosis, page 23, (Dr. [Henry] Howard, March 1840) -- Muscles -- On the treatment of cholera (Dr. Howard) -- Series on the brain and spinal marrow -- Anatomy -- Cholera asphyscia -- Medicine (Dr. Griffith) -- Of yellow fever -- Congestive fever (December 5, 1839) -- Treatment of gastritis -- Symptoms of chronic enteritis -- Diarrhoea acute and chronic -- Causes of hepatitis -- Symptoms of meningitis -- General cerebritis -- Dr. [James L.] Cabell notes (1839) -- Dr. Howard notes.
  Gift of Jethro Meriwether Hurt, III. Fragile with brittle pages.
- Student notebook 1840, ADS notebook (Box-folder 016-002)
  Volume 2 (1840 continued ) -- Howard's lecture on midwifery -- Haemorrage -- Metritis on puerpera fever -- Signs of delivery -- Rape -- Latent diseases -- Survivorship -- Wounds --- Persons found dead -- Adipocere -- Poisons -- Cough mixture [and other remedies and ointments].
  Gift of Jethro Meriwether Hurt, III. Fragile with brittle pages and mold damage.
- Student notebook 1841 January 16 - February 20, ADS with drawings notebook (Box-folder 016-003)
  Volume 3 Notes on materia medica (Dr. Emmet) January 16, 1841 - February 9, 1841 at the University of Pennsylvania): Midwifery -- Labor -- Presentations -- Causes -- Treatment -- Mechanism of presentations -- Hodge (January 20, 1841) -- Wood (February 20, 1841) -- Thraxacum -- Mineral acuscles -- Vegetable astringents -- Kino -- Nervous stimulants (Dr. Wood) -- Cerebral stimulants -- Alcohol -- Opium -- Hemorrhage -- Hyoscyamus -- Camphor -- Belladonna -- Dr. Jackson -- Vascular repair -- Dr. Wood -- Arterial sedatives -- Nux vomica -- Ansenic -- Emetics -- Cathartics.
- Student notebook 1919 April 28 - June 7, ADS with typed notes, drawings (Box-folder 016-004)
  The notebook by Patton K. Pierce, UVA SOM class of 1921, includes Laboratory Exercises in Physiological Chemistry and Pharmacology. Experiments were done on animals including dog, cat, rabbit, turtle, rat, and frog, or various animal organs, with drugs such as alcohol, morphine, ether, caffeine, amyl nitrate, chloroform, opium, and strychnine. Also cocaine was applied to the student's tongue. There is no professor listed but James Alexander Waddell taught Pharmacology, Materia Medica and Toxicology in this time period. According to Southern Medical News, November 1925, "Dr. Patton Kimbrough Pierce, Eutaw [Alabama], aged 30, died August 16 at hospital in Harrisburg, Va. [probably incorrect, probably Alabama] of injuries received when the automobile in which he was driving overturned."
  Gift of James D. Webb who found the notebook at a flea market in Virginia. It arrived at the library March 4, 2013.
- Student notebook: Lectures on Internal Medicine 1923 September 18 - 1924 May 5, ADS notebook, drawings (Box-folder 016-005)
  The notes were taken by Don Carlos Eskew, UVA SOM class of 1924. In the notebook is a slip of paper with Dr Don Carlos Eskew, Buffalo City Hospital, Buffalo, New York written on it. Some of the subjects covered are infectious diseases, heart disease, diseases of the blood, respiratory diseases, arthritis, diseases of the digestive tract, and diabetes mellitus.
  The notebook was acquired from Palinurus Antiquarian Books on May 2, 2015.
- Whiteley's General Chemistry Notes 1885 November 30, ADS notebook, drawings (Box-folder 017-001)
  The title is "Whiteley's General Chemistry Notes" (Complete) Lithographed By Permission And for Sale Only by R. D. Anderson and Bro. University of Virginia. Calvin Whiteley Jr. states that the note of Physics are not full, but the Chemistry notes are full and contain almost everything said during the class. He was helped by the notes of others, especially an old set taken by Mr. Baker Thomas. These notes were then copied by a L.E. Flannagan, M.D. Major sections of the book are Physics, Chemistry Proper, The Atomic Theory, and Organic Chemistry. Five loose pages are about the brain.
  The verso of pages have contemporary notes taken by W.P. Miles Jr. who was a student at UVa in the sessions of 1885-86, 1886-87, and 1887-88. Miles signed his name and wrote 18 East Range, University of Virginia, Nov. 30th 1885 in the book. He was from Burnside, Louisianna and studied Chemistry, Natural Philosophy, Modern Languages, and General and Industrial Chemistry. According to "Old Louisiana Plantation Homes And Family Trees" by Herman De Bachelle Seebold at the death of his father, Dr.William Porcher Miles Jr. abandoned the practice of medicine to attend to his large inheritance. He was not a graduate from the University of Virginia School of Medicine.
  The book was acquired from John Hellebrand of Palinurus Antiquarian Books in June 2015.
- Student notebook: Therapeutics and Materia Medica1855-1866 [?], ADS notebook (Box-folder 017-002)
  The notes were taken by William Joseph Jones of Amherst County, Virginia, and Benjamin Hood. Jones graduated from the University of Virginia in 1865. Other authors may also have contributed; a note later in the book is dated June 18th [18]66.
  Professor: John Staige Davis
  Fragile condition; loose and detached pages. Originally cataloged in Virgo as a rare book, together with the material in Box 17: Folder 3. From the library of Dr. Peyton N. Rhodes (UVA Class of 1920), grandson of the author, Dr. William Joseph Jones (UVA Medical Class of 1865). The notebook was donated to the Health Sciences Library by Dr. Rhodes's brother-in-law, Dr. Harry L. Archer (UVA Medical Class of 1937). Original cataloging note describes Benjamin Hood as the “friend and amanuensis” of William Joseph Jones. Item moved to MS-37 in 2017.
- Student notebook: Physiology and Surgery1865-1870 [?], ADS notebook (Box-folder 017-003)
  The notes were taken by William Joseph Jones of Amherst County, Virginia. Benjamin Hood other authors may also have contributed; the name “John Amonett” of Harris Creek, Amherst, VA appears on the second page which is dated 1870. The notebook also includes several poems and a handwritten land agreement between William J. Jones and two other individuals.
  Professors: Henry Howard, John Staige Davis, J.L. Cabell
  Fragile condition; loose and detached pages. Originally cataloged in Virgo as a rare book, together with the material in Box 17: Folder 2. From the library of Dr. Peyton N. Rhodes (UVA Class of 1920), grandson of the author, Dr. William Joseph Jones (UVA Medical Class of 1866). The notebook was donated to the Health Sciences Library by Dr. Rhodes's brother-in-law, Dr. Harry L. Archer (UVA Medical Class of 1937). Original cataloging note describes Benjamin Hood as the “friend and amanuensis” of William Joseph Jones. Item moved to MS-37 in 2017.